<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>here begynneth a treatyse called. Peruula</title>
            <title>"Parvula"</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1497</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 17 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 6 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A12872</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 23163.7</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S103686</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99839433</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99839433</idno>
            <idno type="VID">3853</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A12872)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3853)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 20:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>here begynneth a treatyse called. Peruula</title>
                  <title>"Parvula"</title>
                  <author>Stanbridge, John, 1463-1510, attributed name.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>In Caxtons hous by wynkyn de worde,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Prynted at westmynstre :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1497?]]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Wrongly attributed to John Stanbridge.</note>
                  <note>An edition of: Parvula.</note>
                  <note>In this edition, text begins: What shalt thou doo when ye haste an englyssh to be made in latyne.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon; publication date conjectured by STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁶.</note>
                  <note>Formerly STC 19439.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 19439 on UMI microfilm reel 20..</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Latin language --  Grammar --  Early works to 1500.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:3853:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3853:1"/>
            <head>Here begynneth a treatyſe called. Peruula.</head>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>depiction of master with his students</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:3853:2"/>WHat ſhalt thou doo whan y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> haſte an englyſſh to be made in latyne. I ſhall reherce myn en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glyſſhe fyrſt ones / twyes or thryes. and loke oute my princypal verbe / and aſke hym this queſtyon / who or what. And that worde that anſweryth to the queſty<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on / ſhall be the nomynatyf caſe to the verbe. But yf it be a-verbe imperſonal / As in this enſample (The mayſter techyth ſcolers) Techyth is the verbe. Who techeth / the mayſter techeth. The mayſter ſhal be no<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mynatyf caſe to the verbe. And that worde that co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth after the verbe / ſhall mooſt comynly be the ac<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cuſatyf caſe. as (Magiſter docet me) And whan I ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue an adiectyf nown / pronowne. particyple or relatyf I ſhall aſke this queſtyon forſayde / who or what / &amp; that worde that anſweryth therto / ſhalbe the ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyf to the adiectyf. &amp; the antecedens to the relatyf.</p>
            <p>¶Whan two ſubſtantyues come togydre longynge bothe to one thynge / they ſhal be put in one caſe. As my fader a man loued me a childe (Pater meus, vir diligit me puerum.) The nomynatyf caſe and the verbe accorde in two. whiche two. In nombre and in perſon. As (Ego. lego. Tu legis. Ille legit.)</p>
            <p>
               <label>¶Vnde verſus</label>
            </p>
            <p>¶Verbum cum recto dic-concordari duobus</p>
            <p>Perſona. numero. ſic tradit regula nobis</p>
            <p>¶The adiectyf &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſubſtantyf ſhall accorde in thre. Whiche thre. In caſe / gendre &amp; nombre</p>
            <p>
               <label>¶Verſus</label>
            </p>
            <p>¶Cum ſubſtantiuis tribus adiectiua locabis</p>
            <p>¶In caſu genere numero da mobile fixo</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:3853:2"/>¶The relatyf &amp; the antecedens ſhal accorde in thre whiche thre. In Gendre Nombre and Perſon. As Pater meus qui. Mater mea que. caput meu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> quod</p>
            <p>¶Cum precedente tribus his coniunge relatum</p>
            <p>¶Perſona. numero. ſit genus aſſociatum</p>
            <p>¶The nowne partityf and the genityf caſe that fo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>loweth ſhall accorde in gendre onely. as (vnus ſocio<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abrum"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>rum</ex>
               </expan>
            </p>
            <p>¶Eſt partitiui genus. vt genus eſt genitiui</p>
            <p>¶The nowne of the ſuperlatyf degree ſhal accorde in gendre onely with the genityf caſe folowynge. as deus eſt optima re<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abrum"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>rum</ex>
               </expan> (homo eſt digniſſima creatura<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abrum"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>rum</ex>
               </expan>.</p>
            <p>¶Omne ſuperlatum genitiuo ſit ſociatum.</p>
            <p>¶At<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> ſuo generi conforme cupit retineri</p>
            <p>¶Vt pateat verum. ſic deus eſt optima rerum</p>
            <p>¶Two nomynatyf caſes ſynguler with a coniunc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cyon copulatyf bytwene / wyll haue a verbe plurel. as Ego &amp; tu legimus)</p>
            <p>
               <label>¶Vnde verſus</label>
            </p>
            <p>¶Dant in plurali verbum iuncti duo recti</p>
            <p>¶Two ſubſtantyues with a coniunccyon copulatyf bytwene / wyll-haue an adiectyf plurell.</p>
            <p>¶Subſtantiua duo ſi ſingula ſint tibi iuncta.</p>
            <p>¶Tunc adiectiuu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſemper plurale requirunt.</p>
            <p>¶Two antecedens ſynguler with a coniunccyon co<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pulatyf bytwene / wyll haue a relatyf plurell.</p>
            <p>¶Poſt duo nomina ſingula des plurale relatum</p>
            <p>¶Whan ony noi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>atyf caſe cometh bytwene y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> relatyf &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> verbe / y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> relatyf ſhalbe ſuche caſe as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> verbe wyl haue after hym. &amp; y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is the moſte comynly the accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatyf caſe. as (Ego quem magiſter docet timeo virga<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:3853:3"/>¶Whan ony nomynatyf caſe cometh bytwene y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latyf &amp; the verbe / then<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e the relatif ſhalbe the noi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>atif caſe ſupponent to the verbe. as (ego qui ſcribo ſedeo) If the verbe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> cometh next the relatif be a verbe im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſonal then<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e ſhal the relatyf be ſuche caſe as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ver<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>be imperſonal requyreth. as (ego cui opponit<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abur"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>ur</ex>
               </expan> atte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>do.</p>
            <p>¶Si quis ſtructuram verbo<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abrum"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>rum</ex>
               </expan> noſcere gliſcat</p>
            <p>¶Ho<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abrum"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>rum</ex>
               </expan> naturam per metra ſequentia diſcat How many verbes haue ſtrenght to couple lyke caſe Verbes ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tiues betokenynge to be / verbes vocaty<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ues / as (nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cupor appellor nominor vocor dicor.) An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glice to be called / cleped or named / Verbes paſſyues / as (eligor. reputor. ordinor ¶and generally whan the worde y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> gooth byfore y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> verbe &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worde y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> folowrth the verbe longe bothe to one thynge / what manner of verbe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> euer be / put bothe in one caſe / as (ego ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> puer (tu vocaris petrus. Paulus eligit<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abur"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>ur</ex>
               </expan> maior londonia<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abrum"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>rum</ex>
               </expan>.) Laicus non ſedet Iudex in cauſis eccleſiaſticis</p>
            <p>¶Sum fio maneo dic exiſto fore conſto</p>
            <p>¶Preſto perſiſto cum ſubſiſto ſimul exto.</p>
            <p>¶Qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>do nota<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſubſtans. ſimiles depoſcere calus</p>
            <p>¶Verba vocatiua vim conſimilem retinebunt</p>
            <p>¶Nominor appellor ſic nuncupor addito dicor.</p>
            <p>¶Et vocor. &amp; queda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> paſſiua (ſic eligor vrbis</p>
            <p>¶Prefectus reputor ſapiens) fit hoc generale</p>
            <p>¶Si quo<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abrum"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>rum</ex>
               </expan> precedat verbu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. verbu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ve ſequatur</p>
            <p>¶Pertineant ad idem. caſu ponantur eodem</p>
            <p>¶Eminet. apparet. ſeden iudex. eo velox.</p>
            <p>¶Hec poſcunt ſimiles poſt ſe pre ſe quo<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> caſus</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:3853:3"/>¶Deſino. deſinis. deſij vel deſiui / deſinere. deſinendi deſinendo deſinendu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. deſitu deſitu. deſine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s deſiturus Anglice / to ſeſſe or to leue of. Et poteſt conſtrui cum Genitiuo. &amp; ablatiuo cum prepoſitione a vel ab. Vt Deſino ludi. vel Deſino a ludo ¶Vnde verſus</p>
            <p>¶Deſinet abſtineo dabis indigeo genitiuo.</p>
            <p>¶At auget &amp; dominor miſerere valet careo<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan>.</p>
            <p>¶Inuideo patior accuſo conſulo conſto</p>
            <p>¶Arguo condemno moneo reprehendo recordor</p>
            <p>¶Et memini dignor obliuiſcor reminiſcor</p>
            <p>¶Participo recolo miror / tu cetera quere</p>
            <p>Theſe verbes folowyng mooſt comynly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtrued with a datyf caſe after theym. &amp; in the paſſyf voyce they ben verbes imperſonales. as mihi obuiatur. tibi parcitur. magiſtro non placetur</p>
            <p>
               <label>¶Vnde verſus</label>
            </p>
            <p>¶Obuto parco placet reſpondeo ſeruio nocet</p>
            <p>¶Precipit opponit concludo iunge datiuis.</p>
            <p>¶Supplicet arridet faueo daco proficit horret</p>
            <p>¶Subuenit addatur ſuccurrit propiciatur</p>
            <p>Congruo compatior confert ſuccedit adulor</p>
            <p>¶Sufficit aſpirat. valedico gratulor aſtat</p>
            <p>¶Imminet equiualet alludit obedit obſtat.</p>
            <p>¶Occurrit eſtuat. &amp; cedo quando locum dat.</p>
            <p>¶Inſidior pateo minor aſt obtempero fido.</p>
            <p>¶Derogo condoleo preiudico detono defert</p>
            <p>¶Suppetit his iungas. que ſum co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ponit eis das.</p>
            <p>¶Hec &amp; <expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abquam"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>quam</ex>
               </expan>plura ternis coniungere cura</p>
            <p>¶Theſe verbes folowynge wyll conſtrue with two accuſatyf caſe.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Verſus</label>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:3853:4"/>¶Poſtulo poſco peto doceo flagito celo</p>
            <p>¶Eruo cum veſtit. manet induo calceo cingo.</p>
            <p>¶Accuſatiuos geminos hec verba requirunt.</p>
            <p>¶Paſſiuis quo<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abrum"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>rum</ex>
               </expan> poſtremus iungitur ho<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abrum"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>rum</ex>
               </expan>
            </p>
            <p>¶Whan this ſygne the foloweth a nowne adiectyf verbe / or particyple betokenynge parte or all / the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuell worde folowynge this ſygne in metre of tymes is put in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> accuſatyf caſe. as (Virgo venuſta faciem In proſe in the ablatyf caſe. as (Venuſta facie)</p>
            <p>¶Adiectiua regunt paſſiua / verba<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> neutra.</p>
            <p>¶Accuſatiuos per ſynodochen ſibi iunctos.</p>
            <p>¶Cum partes toti tribua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tur. totu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ve parti</p>
            <p>¶Sed pocius metris <expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abquam"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>quam</ex>
               </expan> proſis ſynodoche fit)</p>
            <p>¶Thies verbys folowynge haue an ablatif caſe af<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter theym</p>
            <p>
               <label>¶Vnde verſus</label>
            </p>
            <p>¶Veſcitur &amp; fruitur. caret vtitur at<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> potisur.</p>
            <p>¶Hec ablatiuos tranſitione regunt</p>
            <p>¶Et iungas car<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o plus ſexto <expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abquam"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>quam</ex>
               </expan> genitiuo</p>
            <p>¶Veſcor. ceris. caret preterito veſci / to ete / Fruor / is to vſe a thynge for it ſelf / or to haue delyte therin. As Fruor deo bonis ſuis) Fruor amico<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abrum"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>rum</ex>
               </expan> colloquio. Fruor tuo cantu ¶Vtor. eris. vſus ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. vti / to vſe or to were a thyng for a nother cauſe / than for it ſelf. as (vtor ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis. vtor libris. vtor ſtudio. ¶Fu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gor. geris. functꝰ ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gi / to vſe or to hold an offyce. ¶Potior. iris. potitꝰ ſum. potiri. to haue or to obteyne (rex potit<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abur"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>ur</ex>
               </expan> victoria)</p>
            <p>¶Diuinis fruimur exoptatiſ<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> potimur</p>
            <p>¶Vtimur vtilibus. fungimur officio<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan>
            </p>
            <p>¶Veſcimur ac eſcis cum potu delicijſ<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:3853:4"/>¶A nowne ſubſtantyf / or a pronowne with a parti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cyple dependyng of an other / ſhalbe put in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ablatif caſe abſolute. as (magiſtro legente pueri proficiunt.)</p>
            <p>¶Eſt ablatiuus quando<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> regente ſolutus)</p>
            <p>¶Si nomen vel pronomen cum porticipante.</p>
            <p>¶Iungitur. &amp; nullu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dependens eſt tibi verbum.</p>
            <p>¶Vt vento flante gradior. ſocio comitante</p>
            <p>¶Gaudet me viuo mater / dolet at<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> ſepulto</p>
            <p>¶Thies fyue verbes imperſonales (Penitet. Tedet Miſeret. pudet &amp; piget<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> wyll haue the accuſatyr caſe in the ſtede of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> nomynatyf caſe. and a genytyf caſe in ſtede of the accuſatyf caſe. as) Penitet me tui) Te det anima<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> mea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vite mee)</p>
            <p>
               <label>¶Verſus.</label>
            </p>
            <p>¶Penitet &amp; tedet miſeret pudet &amp; piget. iſta</p>
            <p>¶Accuſatiuos poſcunt ſimul &amp; genitiuos.</p>
            <p>¶Natura primu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. ſed tranſicione ſecundu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
            <p>¶Theſe verbes imperſonalles wyll conſtrue with a datyf caſe. as (Libet tibi. placet mihi)</p>
            <p>
               <label>¶Verſus</label>
            </p>
            <p>¶Hec libet at<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> licet placet &amp; libet accidet adde.</p>
            <p>¶Congruit &amp; euenit contingit expedit inde</p>
            <p>¶Pertinet incu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bit vacat tedet. qui<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> preſtat</p>
            <p>¶Cum reliquis paribus interſociata datiuis</p>
            <p>¶All verbes imperſonalles of the paſſyf voyce wyl haue a datyfe or an ablatyf caſe with a prepoſicyon. as (Mihi opponitur. A rege pugnatur</p>
            <p>
               <label>¶Verſus</label>
            </p>
            <p>¶Paſſiue vocis imperſonale datiuis</p>
            <p>¶Aut ſexto iungas. cum prepoſito preeunte.</p>
            <p>¶A pueris itur. a preceptore venitur)</p>
            <p>¶Regi ſeruitur. ſed non ſibi credo placetur.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:3853:5"/>¶Whan the englyſſh of the infynityf mode cometh after ony of thies nownes (tempus cauſa locus &amp;c<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) it may be put in a gerundyf in di. as (te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pus eſt orandi Cauſam habeo flendi. Locus eſt dormiendi.</p>
            <p>
               <label>¶Vnde</label>
            </p>
            <p>¶Tempus cauſa locus libertas iuſ<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> voluntas</p>
            <p>¶Ars modus at<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> licencia / omnia talia que<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan>
            </p>
            <p>¶Prima ſolent poſt ſe vocitare gerundia iure)</p>
            <p>¶Eſt tempus flendi. non eſt mihi cauſa dolendi.</p>
            <p>¶Que nunc narrandi non locus. africus inquit Whan y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> englyſſh of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> infinitif mode cometh after a verbe / or a participle betokeny<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g beſeching or prayng Or y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> engliſſh of a particyple of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> preſentens cometh after a nowne adiectyf with this ſygne of / it may be put in a gerundyf in do. as I am wery of ſyttynge. faynt of faſtyng (Feſſus ſede<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>do. fatigatus ieiuna<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>do.</p>
            <p>¶Pone gerundia do poſt rogantia verba</p>
            <p>¶Poſt adiectiua. mater mea feſſa ſedendo</p>
            <p>¶Te rogo de dando venia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> mihi. de<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> mirando) Wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſygnificaco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>n of a particyple of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> preſentens cometh after a nowne ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tyf w<hi rend="sup">c</hi> this prepoſicion in / afore hym / it may be put in a gerundyf in do.</p>
            <p>¶Participans preſens poſt ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tiua repoſtum</p>
            <p>¶In<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> gerundiuo vel participante locato.</p>
            <p>¶Vt gladiatores pugnando vulnera figunt.</p>
            <p>¶Eſt in cantando frater meus. orpheus alter Whan y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> particyple fayleth / I ſhall take y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame tens of the verbe that the particyple ſholde come of / &amp; the relatyf (qui) put in the nomynatyfe caſe. And it be a verbe imperſonall / the relatyf ſhalbe ſuche caſe as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:3853:5"/>
verbe imperſonale requyreth after hym. as I am op<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poſyd (ego ſum cui opponit<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abur"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>ur</ex>
               </expan>) My fader is ryden (Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter meus eſt a quo equitatur.</p>
            <p>
               <label>¶Verſus</label>
            </p>
            <p>¶Si tibi participans deſit. quo pone relatum.</p>
            <p>¶Tempus idem qui ſui quod depoſcit fore verbi ¶Whan the englyſſh of the infinytyf mode cometh after a reaſon. &amp; telleth the cauſe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reaſon<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> it may be put in a gerundyf in dum. with this prepoſycyon ad. as (Venio ad diſcendum gra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maticam.</p>
            <p>
               <label>¶Vn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </label>
            </p>
            <p>¶Ad du<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cauſa dabit. no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſt cibus ad comedendu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
            </p>
            <p>¶Ad mea tergendum vulnera mappa deeſt.</p>
            <p>¶A geru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dyf in dum. may come in ſpeche with this prepoſicion. inter. as. inter ſedendum. id eſt du<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſederet as. they walke. inter ambula<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dum. as they rode. inter equitandum.</p>
            <p>
               <label>¶Vnde verſus</label>
            </p>
            <p>¶Inter quando<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> cum dum preponitur apte</p>
            <p>¶Inter prandendu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pro dum pranderet habetur.</p>
            <p>¶Hinc maro fit teſtis. age tytere &amp; inter agendu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
            <p>¶Occurſare capro cornu fert ille caueto Wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſygnificacyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> infinitif mode folowyth this englyſſh it is. as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kyng it is to ſyt. Scolars it is to ſtudye. or muſt nedys ſtudye (rege<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pugnandu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſt Scolares ſtudendu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſt omnino It ſhalbe put in a ge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rundyf in dum. with this verbe. eſt. put imperſonall.</p>
            <p>¶Imperſonali verbo eſt quo<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> iungitur ecce</p>
            <p>¶Vincendum eſt hoſtes regem per prelia noſtru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
            <p>¶Whan the engliſſh of the Infinityf mode cometh after a verbe. or a particyple betokenynge meuynge or goyng to a place / it may be put in the fyrſt ſupine
<pb facs="tcp:3853:6"/>
Fro a place / in the latter ſupyne. as (Vado venatum Venio venatu)</p>
            <p>
               <label>¶Verſus</label>
            </p>
            <p>¶Poſt motus verbu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> bene ponis vtru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> ſupinu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
            </p>
            <p>¶Ad loca vuit primu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. de vult ſignare ſecundu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
            <p>¶In the ſtede of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fyrſt ſupyne faylyng / I ſhal put a gerundyf in dum. with this propoſicyon ad. and in ſtede of the latter ſupyne faylyng. I ſhall put the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rundyf in do. with one of thies (a ab de)</p>
            <p>
               <label>¶Vnde</label>
            </p>
            <p>¶Pone gerundiuu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tibi deficiente ſupino.</p>
            <p>¶Ad dum pro primo / de cum do pone ſecundo</p>
            <p>¶Ad bona diſcendum dogmata pergo celer</p>
            <p>¶De bona diſcendi dogmata nunc venio</p>
            <p>¶Whan y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> englyſſh of the infyniytyf mode cometh after a nowne adiectyf endynge in ilis. or in bilis. it may be put in the latter ſupyne (Virgilius) Nec viſu facilis. nec dictu effabilis vlli (Saluſtius. Incredibile memoratu. miſerabile auditu.</p>
            <p>
               <label>¶Vnde Verſus.</label>
            </p>
            <p>¶Poſt adiectiuu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> bilis ac ilis eſto ſecundu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
            </p>
            <p>¶Flebilis auditu minor eſt agilis puer actu</p>
            <p>¶Whan the englyſſh of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> infynityf mode cometh after (ſum es fui) it ſhalbe put in a particyple of the futere tens in rus. yf it be of the actyf voyce. as (ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſter eſt docturus. ſcolares ſunt docendi</p>
            <p>¶Participans in rus. poſt ſum tu pone vel in dus</p>
            <p>¶Vt ſum lecturus Naſonis carmina ſumma</p>
            <p>¶Laus adhibenda deo pro victis hoſtibus eſto</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶Rule of verbes</head>
               <p>¶How many tens be four<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>yd of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> preterperfectens of the Indycatyf mode. Syxe. whiche. Syxe ¶The
<pb facs="tcp:3853:6"/>
preterpluperfectens of the ſame Indicatyf mode and The preterperfectens &amp; preterpluperfectens &amp; the fu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tertens of the Coniunctyf mode. The preterperfec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tens &amp; the preterpluperfectens of the infynityf mode ¶How many chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gyth I into e. &amp; how many hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth I ſtyll Thre chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gyth i into e. &amp; thre holdeth I ſtyll ¶whiche thre chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gyth i into e. The preterplu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>perfectens of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Indicatyf mode as (amaui) chaunge i into e. &amp; put therto a iam / &amp; it wol be (amaueram (¶The preterperfectens of the Coniunctyf mode as amaui) chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge i into e / &amp; put therto a rim. &amp; it woll be (amauerim ¶The futertens of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame mode / as amaui) chaunge i into e. &amp; put therto ro. &amp; it woll be amauero ¶whiche thre holde I ſtyll. The preterplu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>perfectens of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> coniunctyfe mode as (amaui) holde I ſtyll &amp; put to ſ &amp; ſem. &amp; it woll be (amauiſſem) The preterpluperfectens of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> infinityf mode / as (amaui. holde I ſtyll &amp; put to ſ &amp; ſe / &amp; it woll be (amauiſſe</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>¶Prynted at weſtmynſtre In Caxtons hous by wynkyn de worde</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
